In this video we'll be looking at the
TAF workflow, which is very much centered
on R scripts that are run sequentially.
They structure the stock assessment
into separate steps and what we'll end up
with is clean organized and reproducible
assessments. So the aim of TAF is to
implement a framework to organize data,
methods, and results used in ICES
assessments, so they are easy to find and
rerun later with new data. If you look
at the diagram showing the TAF workflow
and the different components, it's about
going from data to analysis and results.
We start with getting data from ICES
databases and other data sources, and
the first step in the data folder is
to gather the data, and to filter and
pre-process the data that will finally
be used in the assessment. So that is one
of the major aims of TAF is to document
and script this process of preparing the
data. Describing where they came from and
what was done to them before they were
entered in the assessment model. Moving
on to the input folder the task there is
to convert the data from the most
general format, crosstab year by age
usually, into the model specific format.
So that will depend on the model: it can
be one big text file, or an R list, or a
number of input text files, whatever the
model will read. The model folder is
about running the model. The model
will be coming from either a toolbox of
commonly used models or any model can be
used within this folder. The final step,
output, is where we convert the model
specific output into more general text
files, things like numbers of age or
fishing mortalities, SSB, recruitment,
and so on. The final step, then, is to
upload those results into the ICES
databases: the stock assessment graphs,
tables and so forth. Behind each of
those folders, data, input, model, and
output, there is an R script that governs
what takes place. So let's take a look at
those scripts in more detail. The first
one is data.R. Again, that is where we
pre-process the data and
write out what we call TAF data
tables. They're very simple crosstab
text files, comma separated values.
The next step is input.R, where we
convert those data to the model specific
format, writing out the model input files.
In model.R we run the analysis, often
just invoking a shell command or
an R package to run the model and
the results will be written out as
output files. Those output files
will often contain information about
likelihoods or gradients, and all sorts
of extra information we don't really
need. So we extract the results of
interest in output.R, things like
numbers at age and fishing mortalities,
and we write them out as text files.
Other scripts that we will be working
with are report.R, which is an
optional script where scientists can
prepare any plots and tables that they
are going to put in the report, and
finally there's upload.R, a very short
script describing the data that are
uploaded into the TAF system. So what
we're going to be doing for the rest of
the video is to go through the actual
analysis behind the 2015 ICES advice for
North Sea spotted ray. The R scripts can
be found on GitHub. In the address you
can see ices-taf/2015_rjm-347d and
if you want to work along while you
watch the video, you can download these
from GitHub and work with them on your
own computer. So let's just dive into
data.R. At the top of the script we
have comments reminding us what is the
purpose of the script: to pre-process
the data and to write out the TAF data
tables. In the comment we also write the
state before the script is run and after
the script is run, in terms of the files
and where they are. So we start with
catch.csv and surveys_all.csv on
the TAF database, and after the script is
run we will have catch.csv, summary.csv,
survey.csv, all found in
a new folder called data.
We start by loading the icesTAF package
and create an empty directory. We next
download the data, the catch and the
survey, and we start pre-processing the
data. We select the years of interest and
the surveys of interest. We scale the
surveys and create a combined index, as
the average of the three surveys, and
this is the catch data. Very short
history of the catches for this
fishery, and this is the survey data.
We have selected the years and those
three surveys, but importantly we have
also created a combined index and that
is the actual input data for the
assessment. We finalize the tables and we
write them out to the data directory.
So what we have done is to create a data
folder containing the data that will be
used in the assessment: catch.csv,
summary.csv, and survey.csv. In the
catch.csv we have the catch history,
in the summary we have combined the
catch history with the index that
will be used, and the survey documents
how the index is calculated. The next
script that is run is input.R. It is a
short script, where we will convert the
data to model format and write out the
model input files. In other words, we will
start with catch and survey in the data
folder, but after the script is run we
will have input.RData in a folder
called input. So we run those commands,
again loading the icesTAF package, creating
the directory. We simply fetch the catch
and the survey data frames, and save
them together in one file, input.RData.
The third script model.R runs the model
and the results will be written out as
dls.txt, inside the model folder.
Now it's not enough just to have
the icesTAF package. We also fetch a
package called icesAdvice, containing the
function that we'll be using to run the
analysis, DLS3.2. So we start by creating
an empty folder, we get the data
from the previous step, we apply the
DLS method 3.2, and the results are
found in the model folder as dls.txt.
It outlines the computations behind the
advice. The advice is 291 tons, and it is
coming from the last advice 243, and
some series of survey indices. On average
they've been going up by 43%, and
the DLS 3.2 rule is that we're
not going to increase the advice by
43%, but rather by maximum of 20%,
so the advice is 291. The output.R
script is about extracting those results
of interest and writing out the TAF
output tables. We're going to read in the
dls.txt, and we're actually just going
to copy it to the output folder. In more
complicated stock assessments this would
of course take more steps, but here we
just copy between model into output.
Finally, in the report.R, we're going
to prepare plots and tables that could
be included in the stock assessment
report. Taking the summary from the data
step, we're just going to be plotting
the survey as a PNG file. So we load the
icesTAF package, we create an empty
directory report, we read in the summary,
and we
create the plot, and we also write out
the summary table, but this time rounding
the catch and the index values, to make it
look better in a report. Inside the
report folder, we now have summary.csv
and survey.png. The survey looks simple
enough, ready to be pasted into the
report, and the summary rounds the
indices, so that they will look better in
a report, maybe with three decimals or so.
So you would just copy this into the
report, essentially. In the R scripts we've
been using some commands that are
outside of base R. We've been using
some ICES packages. So let's take a look
at, for example, DLS3.2. The help page
describes it as a function to apply
ICES method 3.2, and it has some good
guidelines and references on how to use
that function. We've also been using
some R functions from the icesTAF
package. If we just take a look at
the main help page for the icesTAF
package, it lists all the functions by
their groups. So some of them
we've been using to read and write
files, we've been using cp and mkdir
to manipulate files. We used tafpng
to open a PNG graphics device, to draw
an image and write it in PNG format.
Most of the icesTAF functions are very
short and simple, but they're simply
there to make the scripts look
more readable. They're convenient
shorthand functions, to get to the point
without some boilerplate code that is
needed. For example, in the report.R
we were using tafpng like that, so it
uses the suggested image size and
so forth. We also see in the help page
some functions that we will now take a
look at, to run the scripts. There are
convenient functions for that as well:
sourceTAF is to run a single script
and sourceAll is to run all of them.
So let's take a look at how we can use
those, instead of running line by line
like we were doing. We can start from
scratch with nothing in here. We can
run them one by one: sourceTAF data.R.
Very similar to the base R function
to source. It adds some sort of
helpful message, with the time and what
it's doing. But more importantly, we can
run all of them: sourceAll. They run
blazing fast, it's data.R, input.R,
model.R, output.R, and
report.R. That is how
assessment will be run on TAF once
they're uploaded, using sourceAll.
So what we have learned in this video is
about the overall TAF workflow. We used
as an example the North Sea spotted ray,
as a fully scripted analysis. We also
have on the GitHub TAF page other
examples that can be studied in the
same way. That is Icelandic haddock, North
Sea cod, and Eastern Channel plaice. They
are all age based assessments. The Eastern
Channel plaice uses the FLR suite of
R packages, and the North Sea cod is a
SAM model. The Icelandic haddock is an
AD Model Builder age based model, and we'll
be adding more examples there as we go.
In a future video, we will be covering
the TAF web interface, where assessments
can be browsed, run, and modified, and
how web services can be used to upload,
download, and run models.